<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Programming | Peter Friese]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-21T10:41:18+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Peter Friese]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annotated Links, Issue 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/annotated-links-issue-5/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-21T00:44:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/annotated-links-issue-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week, we'll take a look at rocket science, re-usable phones and some Android libraries. Without further ado, let's get started!</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3><a href="https://github.com/nhaarman/ListViewAnimations">Android ListViewAnimations</a></h3>

<p>The main goal of this library is to provide animations in listviews, but it also comes with a great implementation for a UI pattern that most users know from the GMail app: swipe to delete with undo. Rather clumsy name, but it does exactly what's written on the label: the user can swipe a list view item to either side of the screen in order to delete it. But instead of deleting it right away, ListViewAnimations will display a cell with an undo button, allowing the user to change his mind. Integrating it in your apps is straightforward, <a href="https://github.com/nhaarman/ListViewAnimations/wiki/Swipe-To-Dismiss">check out the wiki</a> for further information.</p>

<h3><a href="http://phoneblocks.com/">PhoneBlocks</a></h3>

<p>The number of mobile phones per capita seems to keep growing and a surprising large number of countries <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_countries_by_number_of_mobile_phones_in_use">in this list</a> have a ratio of more than 1:1. Many of these phones aren't being used at all and lead a boring life in a dark corner in the back of a drawer of your desk. <em>Wouldn't it be great if we could use our phones longer than just a few years</em>, thought <a href="https://twitter.com/davehakkens">Dave Hakkens</a> and jotted down his ideas for a reusable, upgradable phone. A great idea, although there are good reasons why <a href="http://whatculture.com/technology/5-reasons-why-phonebloks-probably-wont-work.php">it might not work out at all</a>.</p>

<h3><a href="http://blog.leapmotion.com/post/60390143676/elon-musk-designs-rockets-in-the-air-with-leap-motion">Designing Rocket Engines with the LEAP Motion</a></h3>

<p>Just recently, my colleague <a href="https://twitter.com/sgrasmann">Stefan Grasmann</a> pointed me to a very interesting Hanselminutes episode in which <a href="http://hanselminutes.com/388/vision-based-computing-with-dr-neil-roodyn">Scott Hanselman and Dr. Neil Roodyn talk about vision-based input devices</a> such as Kinect and LEAP Motion. Scott pointed out he had been rather underwhelmed by the user experience of the LEAP, mostly because it requires you to perform rather precise motions instead of the more coarse-grained motions that Scott would like to use. In <a href="http://blog.leapmotion.com/post/60390143676/elon-musk-designs-rockets-in-the-air-with-leap-motion">this video</a>, Elon Musk demonstrates how to use the LEAP to design rocket part prototypes using hand gestures.</p>

<p>Designing rocket engines might not be your cup of tea, but if you want to get your hands on one of those devices, you can either buy a <a href="http://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B00EUCI1GO?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3206&amp;creative=21426&amp;creativeASIN=B00EUCI1GO&amp;linkCode=shr&amp;tag=petfrisblo-21&amp;qid=1379716777&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=leap">regular LEAP at Amazon</a> or wait for the <a href="http://www8.hp.com/us/en/ads/new-products/envy-17-leap-motion.html?jumpid=reg_r1002_usen_c-001_title_r0002">HP Envy Leap</a> - a Laptop by HP with a <a href="http://venturebeat.com/2013/09/19/leap-motion-and-hp-unveil-worlds-first-laptop-with-kinect-like-3-d-gesture-control/">built-in LEAP controller</a></p>

<p>That's it for this week, folks. Enjoy the weekend and create some awesome stuff!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annotated Links, Issue 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/annotated-links-issue-4/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-13T08:11:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/annotated-links-issue-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week, I've got some great tips for traveling and finding out what's installed on your Mac. We'll also look at mobile testing, Git workflows and - cocktails!</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3><a href="http://wikitravel.org/">Wikitravel</a></h3>

<p>Great source of information on everything travel-related. Whether you are considering <a href="http://wikitravel.org/en/First_and_business_class_travel">traveling in business class rather than economy</a>, need background information about <a href="http://wikitravel.org/en/Visa">visas</a> or the lowdown about cities such as <a href="http://wikitravel.org/en/London">London</a>, <a href="http://wikitravel.org/en/Berlin">Berlin</a>, <a href="http://wikitravel.org/en/Hamburg">Hamburg</a>, or <a href="http://wikitravel.org/en/New_York">New York</a>, WikiTravel has you covered. I found the information on the cities to be largely up-to-date and of great value (at least for the cities I know, it seems to very accurate), so it's worth checking out before your next travel.</p>

<h3><a href="http://apple.stackexchange.com/questions/71232/how-do-i-find-what-packages-ive-installed-via-terminal">Help - How do I find out what I installed on my Mac?</a></h3>

<p>The Mac doesn't have a central repository that keeps track of everything you install. If you install software via the Mac App Store, it will be listed in the Mac App Store App (what a word!), but at least if you are a developer (and if you are a regular reader of this blog I assume you are), you'll install software via HomeBrew, the Mac installer and several other means. Now, how did you nstall that particular version of Gradle? Was it HomeBrew? Or did it come as an installer package? Or did you maybe just download and extract a zip file? This answer on Stack Exchange lists several ways to find it out.</p>

<h3><a href="https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.557107127670270.1073741828.100686616645659&amp;type=3">Nokia's Hardware Testing Lab</a></h3>

<p>A nice collection of pictures from Nokia's device testing lab. I'm tempted to call this the "Device Torture Chamber". If you're not so much interested in testing devic hardware, but rather software, you should have a look at these, too:
* <a href="http://codeascraft.com/2013/08/09/mobile-device-lab/">Mobile Test Lab by Etsy</a>
* <a href="http://blog.zuehlke.com/app-testing-going-physical-entwicklung-eines-mobile-teststands/">Mobile Test Rig by Zühlke</a></p>

<h3><a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/workflows">Git Workflows</a></h3>

<p>If you use Git and haven't heard about <a href="http://nvie.com/posts/a-successful-git-branching-model/">Git Flow</a>, you must have been living under a rock. Atlassian, makers of the excellent Git / Hg client <a href="http://www.sourcetreeapp.com">SourceTree</a>, have been so nice to put together an overview of all the various Git workflows, such as the <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/workflows#!workflow-centralized">Centralized Workflow</a>, the <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/workflows#!workflow-feature-branch">Feature Branch Workflow</a>, the <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/workflows#!workflow-forking">Forking Workflow</a> and the <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/workflows#!workflow-gitflow">Gitflow Workflow</a>. If you're looking for a good overview or a refresher, have a look.</p>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/the-teacher/cocktails_for_programmers/blob/master/cocktails_for_programers.md">Cocktails for Programmers</a></h3>

<p>Today (September 13) is Programmers's Day! If you like cocktails, check out <a href="https://github.com/the-teacher/cocktails_for_programmers/blob/master/cocktails_for_programers.md">this collection of cocktails</a> created just for celebrating programmers around the world!
I haven't tried any of these, but <a href="https://github.com/the-teacher/cocktails_for_programmers/blob/master/cocktails_for_programers.md#memory-leak">Memory Leak</a> looks nice. If you missed <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Programmers'_Day">Programmers' Day</a> (it's on the 256th day of the year), you might want to make a note in your diary for 2014. Programmers' day will be on <a href="http://www.timeanddate.com/holidays/world/international-programmers-day">Saturday, September 13, 2014</a>.</p>

<p>That's it for this week - enjoy the weekend!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/h20tubig/9376203024/">Chains image</a> by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/h20tubig/">Haya Bernitez</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annotated Links for Week 34]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/annotated-links-for-week-34/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-23T16:39:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/annotated-links-for-week-34</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week we will have a look at some tools that will help you to make your screenshots shine, a fun approach at looking at your coding behaviours, a collection of views for iOS and Android developers and... beer!</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3><a href="http://mockuphone.com/">MockUPhone</a></h3>

<p>Brought to you by <a href="http://filesq.com">FileSquare</a>, this little web site allows you to create good looking product images of your app inside a real phone frame. As of now, MockUPhone has mockup frames for most (but not all) iOS devices and some Android and Windows Phone devices. Basically, you just upload one or screenshots of your app and - after some crunching - you can download a zip archive that contains your screenshots inside the selected phone cases. You need to provide an e-mail address to download the archive.</p>

<p>Currently, the site is a bit sluggish - maybe due to heavy load. Also, there is very little room for tweaking how the result looks like. Check out <a href="http://shapeitapp.com">ShapeItApp</a> by <a href="http://heikobehrens.net">Heiko Behrens</a> for a similar service that is more flexible and let's you tweak the result before you download it. Also, it would be impossible to talk about mock-up services and not mention <a href="http://placeit.breezi.com">PlaceIt</a> by <a href="http://breezi.com">Breezi</a></p>

<h3><a href="http://osrc.dfm.io">The Open Source Report Card</a></h3>

<p>Some <a href="http://www.github.com">Github</a> related data mining. Enter your Github user name and the site tries to come up with some smart statements about your coding behaviour. <a href="http://dan.iel.fm">Dan</a> uses some Python scripts to extract data from <a href="http://www.githubarchive.org">the Github Archive</a>. The code is <a href="https://github.com/dfm/osrc">available on Github</a> for your enjoyment.</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.androidviews.net">AndroidViews</a></h3>

<p>iOS developers are a blessed bunch of people - not only do we have a <a href="http://cocoapods.org">decent dependency management tool</a>, but also do we have <a href="https://www.cocoacontrols.com">CocoaControls</a>, a never-ending inspiration for new controls, libraries and apps (ever wondered which components your favorite app uses? Head over to the <a href="https://www.cocoacontrols.com/apps">apps section</a>).</p>

<p>For a long time, Android developers didn't have outlets like these. Well, fear no longer, <a href="http://nadavfima.com">Nadav Fima</a> has you covered. <a href="http://www.androidviews.net">AndroidViews</a> offers a nicely organized view into the universe of <a href="http://www.androidviews.net/category/custom-views/holo-style/">views</a>, <a href="http://www.androidviews.net/category/animations/">animations</a>, <a href="http://www.androidviews.net/category/libraries/">libraries</a>, <a href="http://www.androidviews.net/category/dev-tools/">development tools</a> and other <a href="http://www.androidviews.net/category/resources/">resources</a>. If you have a component that is not yet listed, <a href="http://www.androidviews.net/contact-us/">drop him a mail</a>.</p>

<h3><a href="https://medium.com/what-i-learned-today/f7fcb3b786b1">Coffee vs. beer: which drink makes you more creative?</a></h3>

<p>Don't just drink coffee. Also have a glas of wine every now and then to spark your creativity.</p>

<p>Enjoy!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/h20tubig/9376203024/">Chains image</a> by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/h20tubig/">Haya Bernitez</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annotated Links for Week 33]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/annotated-links-for-week-33/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-19T09:30:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/annotated-links-for-week-33</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week's annotated links are more coding- and code-related than last week. We'll have a look at some data mapping frameworks for Objective-C, a way to set up your projects in a faster, more reproducible way and - as iOS 7 is around the corner, a feature comparison of iOS 7 on the various devices out there.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3><a href="http://www.cultofmac.com/231632/the-ultimate-ios-7-compatibility-chart/">iOS 7 Compatibility Chart</a></h3>

<p>With the release of iOS 7 just around the corner, you might be wondering which devices you should test your apps on in order to make sure you cover all required combinations of services that might or might not be available to your app (yes, iOS 7 is one of those releases that won't make all features available on all devices). Cult of Mac has a nice overview chart, worth checking out.</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.merowing.info/2013/05/crafter-setup-your-cocoa-projects-with-ease/">Crafter - Easily Setup Xcode Projects</a></h3>

<p>Github has made it really easy to check out new libraries or demos: just clone the repo and off you go. But what about creating new projects? If you find yourself constantly creating new projects, adjusting the build configuration to suit your needs, adding a Podfile for <a href="http://www.cocoapods.org">CocoaPods</a>, then <a href="https://github.com/krzysztofzablocki/crafter">Crafter</a> might be for you. You can configure it with your defaults, while at the same time staying flexible by adding options. Definitely worth a try.</p>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/krzysztofzablocki/KZPropertyMapper">Object</a> <a href="https://github.com/uacaps/NSObject-ObjectMap">Mapping</a> <a href="https://github.com/dchohfi/KeyValueObjectMapping">in</a> <a href="https://github.com/mattiaslevin/ObjectMapper">Objective-C</a></h3>

<p>Most apps require you to map data from a text-based presentation (mostly JSON or XML) to  Objective-C objects. Chances are you've written mapping code by hand in at least one of your projects. "Its's just one or two classes, how hard can it be?", was probably what you thought when you set out to implement you home-grown mapping. YOu might have ended up with either pulling your hair out while maintianing your code whenever the API team decided to implement some "minor changes" or using a full-blown framework like <a href="http://www.restkit.org">RestKit</a> that gave you more than you needed. If you just need to map data without the need for all the fancy add-ons like automatic CoreData persistence, in-memory and persistent caching and so on, you should have a look at the following frameworks. The all follow different approaches, some apply automagic mapping by matching field names, others by using an internal DSL to help you express your mapping. Take a look yourself and decide based on what you need for your current project.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/krzysztofzablocki/KZPropertyMapper">KZPropertyMapper</a> - uses an internal DSL to express data mappings</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/uacaps/NSObject-ObjectMap">NSObject-ObjectMap</a> - uses introspection to map properties directly unto properties.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dchohfi/KeyValueObjectMapping">KeyValueObjectMapping</a> - Uses a combination of both introspection and configuration to map data unto objects,</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mattiaslevin/ObjectMapper">ObjectMapper</a> - Uses introspection and a callback method to map data.</li>
</ul>


<h3><a href="http://instacod.es">And finally... Instacodes</a></h3>

<p>Did you ever wonder how to create those geeky looking source code screenshots that look like you used a camera to take a picture of your screen from an angle? Well, here's a tool that let's you create those screenshots without the need to take out your camera: <a href="http://instacod.es">Instacodes</a></p>

<p><ul class="gallery">
<li><a href="/images/2013-08-17-annotated-links-for-week-33/instacodes.png" class="fancybox" rel="gallery-58957bab7ae3483cd792adcee872db68" title="Istancodes sample"><img src="/thumbs/instacodes_600x250.png" alt="Istancodes sample" /></a></li>
</ul></p>

<p>That's it for this week, I hope you liked it. Feel free to send suggestions for next week!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/h20tubig/9376203024/">Chains image</a> by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/h20tubig/">Haya Bernitez</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annotated Links for Week 32]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/annotated-links-for-week-32/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-10T01:33:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/annotated-links-for-week-32</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week, we'll have a look at Apple's new system status page and another, more serious issue in a rather well-known computer-driven system. Other topics in this post: a very high-level view on programming (and why we failed so far) as well as a very detailed look at programming (and what you can do to excel at it). Finally, some spying.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3><a href="https://developer.apple.com/support/system-status/">Apple System Status Page</a></h3>

<p>As an iOS developer, you rely on a surprisingly high number of Apple systems. Until recently, there wasn't a way to find out if a system was offline or if it was just you, "<a href="http://www.engadget.com/2010/06/24/apple-responds-over-iphone-4-reception-issues-youre-holding-th/">holding it wrong</a>". As an immediate response to the (<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/technology/2013/jul/26/apple-developer-site-hack">alleged</a>) hack of their developer support systems, Apple shut down pretty much all of their developer support systems and set up this system status page. As of now, all systems are back to normal, but this page might come in handy for future outages.</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.ima.umn.edu/~arnold/disasters/ariane.html">The Explosion of Ariane 5</a></h3>

<p>Due to popular belief, Ariane 5 exploded because a programmer mixed up a comma with a period, but it's not that easy<strong>,</strong></p>

<p>In fact, the problem was someone used a 16 bit unsigned integer variable to hold the result of converting a 64 bit floating point value. I guess this is strong point for using type safe languages in safety-critical systems as well as clearly stating the pre- and post conditions of library functions. Some unit tests might also be in good order.</p>

<h3><a href="http://worrydream.com/dbx/">The Future of Programming</a></h3>

<p>A talk Bret Victor gave at the DropBox conference in <del>1973</del> 2013 on how he thinks the future of programming could have looked like if developers had been more courageous in embracing new ideas instead. Instead, we often see people rejecting new ideas, stating "that's not real programming". Thankfully, every now and then new ideas are strong enough to gain enough traction. Otherwise, we'd still be writing code in binary. Recently, we've seen a growing interest in programming languages and programming paradigms other than the well-known object-oriented / procedural approaches. I think this is a good sign, however, we need to be more open minded and think more about other, new ways of programming. If you haven't done so in this year, you should set aside some time to learn a new programming language. Why not try <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/xtend/">Xtend</a>?</p>

<h3><a href="http://open.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/08/01/objectively-stylish/?_r=0">The NYTimes Objective-C Styleguide</a></h3>

<p>If you develop software for a living, you know that following a coding style guide makes sense. Sometimes, people do get religious about how to format their code - try to steer clear of this by using a widely-regarded style guide. The NYTimes Objective-C Styleguide is well-written, has the right amount of concise examples and can be <a href="https://github.com/NYTimes/objective-c-style-guide">forked</a> in case you feel you need to adjust something to your liking. The fact that the New York Times mobile team <a href="https://github.com/NYTimes/objective-c-style-guide/graphs/contributors">welcomes contributions</a> will probably make this styleguide one of the more popular ones.</p>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/ttscoff/selfspy">SelfSpy</a></h3>

<p>Whether you just want to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantified_Self">quantify yourself</a>, something which <a href="http://blog.stephenwolfram.com/2012/03/the-personal-analytics-of-my-life/">Stephen Wolfram seems to be doing to quite some extent</a> or you're curious what secret services might know about you if they installed a keylogger on your system: SelfSpy is a good tool to get started: it runs on Linux, Windows and Mac OSX. Besides, it's open source - so you can see what it does and you can extend it if needed.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/h20tubig/9376203024/">Chains image</a> by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/h20tubig/">Haya Bernitez</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
