<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Job | Peter Friese]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/blog/categories/job/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-06T20:29:54+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Peter Friese]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google+: +1]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/google-plus-plus-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-29T13:34:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/google-plus-plus-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Can&rsquo;t make sense of the cryptic headline? Read on, I&rsquo;ll explain! If you <em>can</em> decode the headline, you qualify as a geek and should read on as well :&ndash;)</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I am excited to announce I have started a new job with Google!</p>

<p>Starting January 20th 2014, I&rsquo;ll work as a Developer Advocate on the Google+ team at Google in London. Many people have asked me what a Developer Advocate actually is and what we do, so I&rsquo;ll briefly explain it here for everyone&rsquo;s benefit.</p>

<p>The official job posting for <a href="https://www.google.com/about/jobs/search/#!t=jo&amp;jid=729001&amp;">Developer Advocates at Google</a> says:</p>

<blockquote><p>We&rsquo;re self-proclaimed nerds, and our Developer Relations organization helps keep us connected to the communities that love technology as much as we do. Developer Advocates are focused on supporting the 3rd party developers who are building applications and businesses on Google&rsquo;s platforms. You are passionate evangelists for Google technologies as well as vocal champions for developer interests within Google. This is a position for engineers who love connecting with developers and speaking publicly about cutting-edge technologies on conference panels, at user groups, on blogs and with the press. Chrome, Android, App Engine, HTML5 as well as our core Google Apps and Ads APIs are just some of the platforms you promote and support.</p></blockquote>

<p>As a part of that, I&rsquo;ll be working together with a whole bunch of other Developer Relations staff to help 3rd party developers and partners to use the Google+ Platform and APIs to integrate their apps and services with Google&rsquo;s platforms. The term &ldquo;Advocate&rdquo; means I&rsquo;ll act as a two-way communication channel: on one hand, I will speak at conferences, write blog posts and articles to communicate how to use Google APIs. On the other hand, I am here to listen to the feedback user of our APIs give and make sure this gets fed back into the product life cycle. This means I will meet with a lot of partners and developers, listen to their needs and gripes and help them to make sense of our APIs</p>

<p>If you are interested in a more in-depth explanation or if you&rsquo;re even considering becoming a Developer Advocate yourself, I can recommend <a href="http://christianheilmann.com/">Christian Heilmann&rsquo;s</a> <a href="http://bit.ly/1iLdFX3">excellent book</a> on this topic.</p>

<p>That being said, feel free to reach out to me on <a href="https://twitter.com/peterfriese">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/+PeterFriese/">Google+</a>, or by <a href="mailto:peterfriese@google.com">email</a> if you are interested in using the Google+ platform and becoming a platform partner. If you&rsquo;ve got any technical questions, check out our excellent and friendly communities on <a href="https://plus.google.com/communities/113527920160449995981">Google+</a> and <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/tags/google-plus">StackOverflow</a>. If there is anything in particular you would like me to have a look at, ping me on Google+. When reporting a problem, keep in mind the guidelines for <a href="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/bugs.html">writing great bug reports</a> and also keep <a href="https://plus.google.com/+ManoMarks/">Mano Marks'</a> post on <a href="https://plus.sandbox.google.com/u/1/+ManoMarks/posts/fnhGau9BpPW">How to Approach a Google Developer Advocate with Questions</a> in mind &ndash; help us to better help you :&ndash;)</p>

<p>Lastly &ndash; we&rsquo;re hiring: check out <a href="https://www.google.com/about/jobs/search/">Google Jobs</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Joining itemis]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/joining-itemis/"/>
    <updated>2008-02-19T11:33:20+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/joining-itemis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Effective February 1st, 2008, I left my <a href="http://www.gentleware.com/">former employer</a> and <a href="https://www.xing.com/profile/Peter_Friese">joined</a> <a href="http://www.itemis.de/">itemis</a>.</p>

<p>There are many reasons for this step, and I don&rsquo;t want to go into too much detail, so here are the two most important ones:</p>

<p>First of all, I had to do a lot of travel in my recent position at Gentleware. Actually, I like traveling quite much &ndash; as you get around interesting places and meet  a lot of interesting people &ndash; especially if you are a software architect (which is a synonym for &ldquo;information hub&rdquo; :&ndash;) ). However, with three small children, this meant a lot of hassle and tears. Wrong timing, one might argue. Maybe I&rsquo;ll hit the road again when the kids are older. The new position does not require that much traveling, so I&rsquo;ll be at home most evenings which is great for my family (and also for me).</p>

<p>As you may know, <a href="http://www.itemis.de">itemis</a> is quite committed to Model Driven Software Development (MDSD). The majority of projects they work on rely on MDA/MDSD technology. Not only is itemis a user of model driven technology, but also do they heavily contribute to open source projects in this area. Itemis employees are committers on projects like <a href="http://ww.openarchitectureware.org">openArchitectureWare</a>, <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/modeling/">Eclipse Modeling Project</a> and Fornax. Since the company management has identified &ldquo;innovation management&rdquo; as one of their top duties, they consequently launched a <a href="http://www.itemis.de/presse/5287/neue-niederlassung-in-kiel.html">new branch office in Kiel</a> with a group of employees who are dedicated to working on open source modeling tools.  As working on open source projects is something I really enjoy and since I believe model driven development is a very hot topic, I decided to switch companies and join this team.</p>

<p>I learned a lot at Gentleware and am very grateful for the experiences I was able to make there.</p>

<p>Now, I am looking forward to creating the upcoming version 5.0 of <a href="http://ww.openarchitectureware.org">openArchitectureWare</a> together with my colleagues (<a href="https://www.xing.com/profile/Sven_Efftinge">Sven Efftinge</a>, <a href="https://www.xing.com/profile/Jan_Koehnlein">Jan Köhnlein</a>, <a href="https://www.xing.com/profile/Dennis_Huebner2">Dennis Hübner</a>, <a href="https://www.xing.com/profile/Torsten_Krohn">Torsten Krohn</a>) here in <a href="http://www.kitz-kiel.de/">Kiel</a>. Expect to hear exciting things in the following weeks and months. We started a team blog you might want to subscribe to: <a href="http://apps.itemis.de/roller/itemislabkiel">http://apps.itemis.de/roller/itemislabkiel </a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leaving Lufthansa Systems]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/leaving-lufthansa-systems/"/>
    <updated>2007-01-04T01:19:02+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/leaving-lufthansa-systems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am leaving <a href="http://www.lhsystems.com">Lufthansa Systems</a> to join <a href="http://www.gentleware.com">Gentleware</a>.</p>

<p>I joined <a href="http://www.lufthansa.com">Lufthansa</a> in August 1996, when I started my studies in computer sciences at <a href="http://www.nordakademie.de">Nordakademie,</a> Elmshorn. After finishing my studies in early 2000, I started my career as a software engineer with <a href="http://www.lhsystems.com">Lufthansa Systems</a>. My first team developed a tool that helped administrators to install Windows PCs unattended. Most of the code was written in Delphi and DOS Batch. After 1 year, I had the opportunity to join another team who were writing enterprise applications in Java. Although I had never written a single line of Java code before, I was given the chance to join the team (mostly because I had some experience with distributed systems and CORBA). The team was rather small when I joined (only three developers, including me, and one boss), but grew up to 15 developers in about 2 years. We had some good fun writing J2EE applications (and frameworks).</p>

<p>In 2004, I was looking for a tool thet helped me to quickly create a Struts-based application and came across <a href="http://www.andromda.org">AndroMDA</a>. This was an important step on my way into the world of model driven software development. I started using AndroMDA in my J2EE projects, and soon started contributing patches to AndroMDA. Sortly after, I was invited to join AndroMDA as a committer.</p>

<p>Gentleware is a well-known company in the realm of modeling tools and I first met Gentleware&rsquo;s CEO Marco Boger at JAX 2004 when Matthias Bohlen and I gave a talk on AndroMDA. In 2006, Gentleware were looking for a Software Architect to join their team and help them to further develop their new Eclipse based roundtrip engineering tool <a href="http://www.gentleware.com/apollo.html">Apollo</a>.</p>

<p>My main areas of work in my new job will be to help make Apollo a great UML tool that integrates with model driven approaches like MDA and MDSD. Also, I will serve as a Software Architect on J2EE projects.</p>

<p>If you happen to be at OOP 2007 in Munich, just drop by the Gentleware booth and say hi. I will be there not only to present <a href="http://www.gentleware.com/apollo.html">Apollo</a> and <a href="http://www.gentleware.com/products.html">Poseidon</a> (our modelling tools), but also to give a talk on <a href="http://www.sigs-datacom.de/sd/kongresse/oop_2007/program.php?cat=session&amp;ID=13">Open Source MDA</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
