<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Mobile | Peter Friese]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/blog/categories/mobile/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-28T17:57:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Peter Friese]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annotated Links, Issue 6]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/annotated-links-issue-6/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-11T12:24:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/annotated-links-issue-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After a few weeks of silence (and on popular demand by a <a href="http://heikobehrens.net">single person</a>), I decided to pick up publishing my annotated links again. This time, we&rsquo;ll look at wiretapping APIs, donating code to your favourite projects on Github, Node.js in your iOS apps, and a racing game that renders its track across multiple devices.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3><a href="http://www.runscope.com">Runscope</a></h3>

<p>Runscope is an online tool for inspecting, debugging and testing API traffic. The traffic inspector allows you to easily set up a &ldquo;wire tap&rdquo; for your app, basically allowing you to monitor and record any traffic between your app and any API that you&rsquo;re using. In addition to recording traffic for inspection, you can also compare responses of two calls and find out where the differences are &ndash; very handy! You can even share individual recorded requests with your co-workers, e.g. to discuss a problem with your back-end team.</p>

<p>Runscope also provides a tool for automated testing of your API, dubbed <em>Runscope Radar</em>. This tool allows you to set up a sequence of API calls, along with the expected outcome for each of the calls. Radar provides an easy-to-use UI for setting up simple, yet powerful assertions that allow you to specify how the header and body of the response should look like. Variables help you to keep things flexible. Runscope Radar supports JSON and XML, so it is easy to build expressions like <code>[2].number</code> to navigate JSON and XML responses and specify expectations. You can then schedule your tests to run at given intervals and be notified via e-mail in case a test fails. This allows you to easily set up intelligent tests that monitor the validity of your API.</p>

<p><a href="http://httpkit.com/wiretap">Wiretap</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/KrisJordan">Kris Jordan</a> looks very promising as well. It acts as a reverse proxy, allowing you to record HTTP traffic between your app and an API very easily. In fact, setting up a wiretap seems to be easier than setting up Runscope. Unfortunately, still is in beta, but Kris has set up a video to give you a goood understanding of how it works. Wiretap and Runscope look strikingly similar, but I have the impression Wiretap has been around for longer&hellip;</p>

<h3><a href="http://24pullrequests.com">24 Pull Requests Until Christmas</a></h3>

<p>Christmas is upon us &ndash; and this is your chance to give back some love to some of the many open source projects out there you might be using in your own work. The idea is to submit one pull request each day for any project on Github. A number of projects are already listed on the <a href="http://24pullrequests.com/projects">projects</a> page, which allows you to filter projects by programming language to find a few that you might be interested in. Your favourite project isn&rsquo;t listed? No problem at all &ndash; just <a href="http://24pullrequests.com/projects/new">submit a suggestion</a> and fork away!</p>

<p>I found it very interesting to see <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/xtend/">Xtend</a> is officially listed as a programming language on Github &ndash; great job, <a href="https://twitter.com/xtendlang">guys</a>!</p>

<h3><a href="http://nodeapp.org">Node.js in your iOS App</a></h3>

<p>If you wanted to use JavaScript in your iOS apps prior to iOS 7, you basically had two options: use an embedded <code>UIWebView</code> and invoke <code>-stringByEvaluatingJavaScriptFromString:</code>, or recompile <a href="https://github.com/phoboslab/JavaScriptCore-iOS">JavaScriptCore for iOS</a>.</p>

<p>Starting with iOS 7, Apple <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/releasenotes/General/WhatsNewIniOS/Articles/iOS7.html">opened access to JavaScriptCore</a> (I really like <em>&ldquo;For information about the classes of this framework, see the framework header files.&rdquo;</em>), basically enabling iOS developers to use JavaScript to script their applications.</p>

<p>The NodeApp interpreter goes one step further and allows developers to re-use existing Node modules. Even if you might not be interested in using any of the <a href="https://npmjs.org">50.000+ module listed on npm.org</a>, this is good news as it allows you to re-use the Node module system, thereby enabling you to structure your JavaScript apps in a more concise way.</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://github.com/node-app/Interpreter">NodeApp interpreter app</a> and impress your coworkers with a real JavaScript interpreter running on your iPhone!</p>

<h3><a href="http://g.co/racer">Racer &ndash; A multiplayer game for your mobile browser</a></h3>

<p>Racer is a Chrome Experiment that shows off various web technologies, like <a href="http://www.html5rocks.com/en/tutorials/websockets/basics/">WebSockets</a>, the <a href="http://www.html5rocks.com/en/tutorials/webaudio/intro/">Web Audio API</a>, CSS Animations and <a href="http://css-tricks.com/css-sprites/">CSS Sprites</a>.</p>

<p>Watch the <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=17P67Uz0kcw">making of</a>, read the back story of how it was made on <a href="http://master.html5rocks-hrd.appspot.com/en/tutorials/casestudies/racer/">HTML 5 rocks</a>. Then, go find some friends with mobile devices and <a href="http://g.co/racer">play Racer online</a>. The <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YT0k99hCY5I">soundtrack</a> has been composed by <a href="https://myspace.com/giorgiomoroderpage">Giorgio Moroder</a>, who composed a number of well-known songs for events like Olympia 1984 and 1988 or the 1990 Football World Cup. Some of his songs were used in racing games before, but the soundtrack for Racer is the first one to be composed specifically for the purpose of being used in a racing game.</p>

<p>I hope you enjoyed this week&rsquo;s links &ndash; let me know if you would like me to continue compiling them by sending me a mail or &ndash; better yet &ndash; using the tweet button below to let your friends know about this post!</p>

<p>Thanks for reading!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annotated Links, Issue 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/annotated-links-issue-5/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-21T00:44:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/annotated-links-issue-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week, we&rsquo;ll take a look at rocket science, re-usable phones and some Android libraries. Without further ado, let&rsquo;s get started!</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3><a href="https://github.com/nhaarman/ListViewAnimations">Android ListViewAnimations</a></h3>

<p>The main goal of this library is to provide animations in listviews, but it also comes with a great implementation for a UI pattern that most users know from the GMail app: swipe to delete with undo. Rather clumsy name, but it does exactly what&rsquo;s written on the label: the user can swipe a list view item to either side of the screen in order to delete it. But instead of deleting it right away, ListViewAnimations will display a cell with an undo button, allowing the user to change his mind. Integrating it in your apps is straightforward, <a href="https://github.com/nhaarman/ListViewAnimations/wiki/Swipe-To-Dismiss">check out the wiki</a> for further information.</p>

<h3><a href="http://phoneblocks.com/">PhoneBlocks</a></h3>

<p>The number of mobile phones per capita seems to keep growing and a surprising large number of countries <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_countries_by_number_of_mobile_phones_in_use">in this list</a> have a ratio of more than 1:1. Many of these phones aren&rsquo;t being used at all and lead a boring life in a dark corner in the back of a drawer of your desk. <em>Wouldn&rsquo;t it be great if we could use our phones longer than just a few years</em>, thought <a href="https://twitter.com/davehakkens">Dave Hakkens</a> and jotted down his ideas for a reusable, upgradable phone. A great idea, although there are good reasons why <a href="http://whatculture.com/technology/5-reasons-why-phonebloks-probably-wont-work.php">it might not work out at all</a>.</p>

<h3><a href="http://blog.leapmotion.com/post/60390143676/elon-musk-designs-rockets-in-the-air-with-leap-motion">Designing Rocket Engines with the LEAP Motion</a></h3>

<p>Just recently, my colleague <a href="https://twitter.com/sgrasmann">Stefan Grasmann</a> pointed me to a very interesting Hanselminutes episode in which <a href="http://hanselminutes.com/388/vision-based-computing-with-dr-neil-roodyn">Scott Hanselman and Dr. Neil Roodyn talk about vision-based input devices</a> such as Kinect and LEAP Motion. Scott pointed out he had been rather underwhelmed by the user experience of the LEAP, mostly because it requires you to perform rather precise motions instead of the more coarse-grained motions that Scott would like to use. In <a href="http://blog.leapmotion.com/post/60390143676/elon-musk-designs-rockets-in-the-air-with-leap-motion">this video</a>, Elon Musk demonstrates how to use the LEAP to design rocket part prototypes using hand gestures.</p>

<p>Designing rocket engines might not be your cup of tea, but if you want to get your hands on one of those devices, you can either buy a <a href="http://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B00EUCI1GO?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3206&amp;creative=21426&amp;creativeASIN=B00EUCI1GO&amp;linkCode=shr&amp;tag=petfrisblo-21&amp;qid=1379716777&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=leap">regular LEAP at Amazon</a> or wait for the <a href="http://www8.hp.com/us/en/ads/new-products/envy-17-leap-motion.html?jumpid=reg_r1002_usen_c-001_title_r0002">HP Envy Leap</a> &ndash; a Laptop by HP with a <a href="http://venturebeat.com/2013/09/19/leap-motion-and-hp-unveil-worlds-first-laptop-with-kinect-like-3-d-gesture-control/">built-in LEAP controller</a></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it for this week, folks. Enjoy the weekend and create some awesome stuff!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code Generation 2011 - Don't miss out!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/code-generation-2011-dont-miss-out/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-21T11:09:11+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/code-generation-2011-dont-miss-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Code Generation 2011 is <a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/index.php">just around the corner</a> and if you haven&rsquo;t booked yet, <a href="http://evbk.software-acumen.com/makebooking.php?event=CG2011">you should hurry up</a> &ndash; a few places are still available!</p>

<p>Quite a number of my colleagues at itemis have been busy preparing for this conference in the past few weeks. Besides working hard to hit the <a href="http://wiki.eclipse.org/Indigo/Simultaneous_Release_Plan">Eclipse Release Train milestone for Indigo on June 22nd</a>, the Xtext team brushed up their hands-on sessions &ldquo;<a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=17">Xtext Take I: Creating Code Generators with Xtend2</a>&rdquo; and &ldquo;<a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=16">Xtext Take II: Crafting Domain Specific Languages with Xtext and Xbase</a>&rdquo;. If you&rsquo;ve been using Xtext, you&rsquo;re well aware of the power you have at your disposal with this tool. Xbase and Xtend2, however, take this experience to a whole new level. So make sure to mark your calendar for these two sessions!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>But not only the Xtext team will share their expertise at CG2011 &ndash; Markus and Karsten will be also be in town to give hands-on tutorials and report from their experience:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=22">Type Systems for DSLs (Markus Völter)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=8">Graphiti + Xtext: mixing graphical and textual DSLs for sprayers/designers (Karsten Thoms / Bernhard Merkle)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=5">Introduction to JetBrains Meta Programming System (MPS) (Markus Völter)</a></li>
</ul>


<p>The finale of the conference will be a panel discussion hosted by Markus on the topic of &ldquo;<a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=20">Models, DSLs, Transformations: The Next 5 years</a>&rdquo; &ndash; this should be a very interesting and lively discussion!</p>

<p><a href="http://lanyrd.com/people/hbehrens/">Heiko</a> <a href="http://lanyrd.com/people/peterfriese/">and I</a> will present &ldquo;<a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=28">Cross-Platform Mobile Development with DSLs</a>&rdquo; &ndash; a <a href="http://lanyrd.com/2011/cg2011/sdpgm/">fast-paced and fun mixture of slides, live coding (or modeling, if you will), videos and audience interaction</a>. Yes, that&rsquo;s right &ndash; the audience will be part of the show. Make sure to bring your web-enabled mobile phone and get the chance to win a price!</p>

<p>To keep track of the conference program(me), we at <a href="http://mobile.itemis.com">itemis mobile</a> have been busy to create a conference planner for your iOS and Android powered mobile phones. Here are the download links:</p>

<ul>
<li>Apple App Store: <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/code-generation-2011/id436689925?mt=8">Code Generation 2011</a></li>
<li>Android Market Place: <a href="https://market.android.com/details?id=de.itemis.mobile.android.cg2011&amp;feature=search_result">Code Generation 2011</a></li>
</ul>


<p><ul class="gallery">
<li><a href="/images/2011-05-21-code-generation-2011-dont-miss-out/cg2011.png" class="fancybox" rel="gallery-f9049cdceaffaf2ba66743d40d991d29" title="Code Generation 2011 Apps for iPhone and Android"><img src="/thumbs/cg2011_300x300.png" alt="Code Generation 2011 Apps for iPhone and Android" /></a></li>
</ul></p>

<p>If you like the apps, please use the feedback feature of the respective store. Got comments or suggestions for improvement? <a href="mailto:mobile@itemis.de">Drop us a note</a> or track us down at the conference (best chance to see us: <a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=28">come to our talk</a> ;&ndash;) ).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Save a Tree, Put EclipseCon 2011 in Your Pocket]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/save-a-tree-put-eclipsecon-2011-in-your-pocket/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-25T22:15:57+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/save-a-tree-put-eclipsecon-2011-in-your-pocket</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After the huge success of the mobile apps for Eclipse Summit Europe, we decided to provide mobile apps for EclipseCon 2011, too. So instead of using a printed copy of the conference program, you can browse the schedule on your smart phone &ndash; wherever you are!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This year, we&rsquo;re providing a rather impressive lineup of mobile apps for iPhone, iPod Touch, iPad (thanks to <a href="http://www.compeople.eu/blog/?p=786">Christian Campo who created a stand-alone iPad app</a>), BlackBerry (<a href="http://ekkes-apps.org/">Ekke is working on a updated version, AFAIK</a>), and all other smart phones that feature a browser.</p>

<p>All apps allow you to browse the program, select your favorite talks and get to know the speakers (with headshots so you recognise them in the hallways). We also have included maps of the convention center as well as Santa Clara.</p>

<p>For a first glimpse, watch our video:</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/20377509 "></iframe></div></p>

<p>As of today, both iPhone and Android users can download the apps from the Apple App Store respectively the Android Marketplace. Here are the links:</p>

<ol>
<li> <a href="http://bit.ly/econ2011iphone">EclipseCon 2011 iPhone App</a></li>
<li> <a href="http://bit.ly/econ2011android">EclipseCon 2011 Android App</a></li>
</ol>


<p>If you don&rsquo;t own an iPhone or Android, you can always use the HTML-only version of the conference program available at <a href="http://bit.ly/econ2011html">http://bit.ly/econ2011html</a>.</p>

<p>The iPad and BlackBerry apps will be available soon, so stay tuned!</p>

<p>By the way, if <strong>you</strong> run a conference and are interested in having an app like this, <a href="http://mobile.itemis.com">get in touch with us</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Three reasons why I think the HP TouchPad will rock the tablet market]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.peterfriese.de/three-reasons-why-i-think-the-hp-touchpad-will-rock-the-tablet-market/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-10T10:38:26+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.peterfriese.de/three-reasons-why-i-think-the-hp-touchpad-will-rock-the-tablet-market</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, <a href="http://www.engadget.com/2011/02/09/hp-posts-complete-think-beyond-event-video/">HP introduced</a> the <a href="http://www.palm.com/us/products/pads/touchpad/index.html">Touchpad</a>, an <del>iPad-like</del> tablet device that is programmed with web technologies. While this certainly isn&rsquo;t the first attempt of a vendor to compete with Apple on the tablet market, I am convinced the TouchPad is a true challenger to the iPad. There are three reasons why the TouchPad might be a real contender: the programming environment, the manufacturing process and security.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>HP is definitely doing something right. Never before has one single Tablet thrilled the interwebs as much as the TouchPad &ndash; except for the iPad, of course. Even <a href="http://scobleizer.com/2011/02/09/hp-makes-google-look-even-more-creaky/">die-hard Apple</a> fans are thrilled.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s why I think HP&rsquo;s TouchPad will score a considerable market share:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>It&rsquo;s programmed with web technologies like HTML, CSS and JavaScript. Don&rsquo;t get me wrong &ndash; the iPad can also be programmed with web technologies: when the iPhone was first released and no one but Apple was allowed to write native apps, Steve himself told everyone that &ldquo;mobile web applications are the future&rdquo;. And despite the fact Apple has opened it&rsquo;s SDK and we can now program the iPad / iPhone in Objective-C, many developers are more interested in writing apps with web technologies. Tools like PhoneGap and Appcelerator try to alleviate this situation, basically allowing you to wrap web code in more or less tiny wrapper apps so your web apps can be submitted to the App Store. However, most apps written using web technologies do not feel the same as real native apps on the iOS platform. So why do I think the situation will be better on the TouchPad? Well, because the TouchPad has been built for running web-based apps! It has been optimized for it. Web apps look stunningly great on the TouchPad. Now, every web developer can download the webOS SDK and get started writing apps for the TouchPad. It&rsquo;s a safe bet to assume there are more web developers out there than Objective-C developers, so it shouldn&rsquo;t take long until we&rsquo;ve got a similar amount of apps for the TouchPad as we&rsquo;ve got for the iPad.</p></li>
<li><p>The manufacturing process. HP has a very powerful production pipeline, capable of pumping out high volumes of devices. In <a href="http://www.itchannelplanet.com/trends/article.php/3920936/Gartner-Global-PC-Shipments-Total-351-Million-Units-in-2010-Gain-138-Percent-US-Q4-PC-Market-Slides-Nearly-7-Percent.htm">Q4/2010, they shipped 17.6</a> million PCs (<a href="http://www.apple.com/pr/library/2011/01/18results.html">Apple sold 7.33 million iPads</a> in the same quarter). So if they are serious about it, it should be easy for HP to both produce and distribute high volumes of TouchPads.</p></li>
<li><p>Security. When it comes to enterprise computing, security becomes a vital feature of your product. CIOs need to make sure to not compromise their company&rsquo;s security by introducing products and devices that have no proper support for security mechanisms. There have always been <a href="http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2009/07/iphone-encryption/">security concerns</a> with respect to the iOS platform: for a long time, there hasn&rsquo;t been a way to nuke a lost iOS device remotely. <a href="http://support.apple.com/kb/HT4175">It wasn&rsquo;t before iOS 4</a> that Apple introduced data protection APIs to secure data that apps store on the device. <a href="">WebOS has several security features built in</a> (not bolted on later) which make it rather attractive for enterprise computing right from the start.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>It&rsquo;s my firm belief that the release of the HP TouchPad is a milestone for the perception of personal computing in the long run. It looks great, we&rsquo;ll see tons of great apps for it in no time and HP as a major computer vendor has the power to push it to the market.</p>

<p>Good-bye, PC.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
