<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Android | Peter Friese]]></title>
  <link href="http://peterfriese.github.io/blog/categories/android/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://peterfriese.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-10T03:34:49+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://peterfriese.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Peter Friese]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code Generation 2011 - Don't miss out!]]></title>
    <link href="http://peterfriese.github.io/code-generation-2011-dont-miss-out/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-21T11:09:11+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://peterfriese.github.io/code-generation-2011-dont-miss-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Code Generation 2011 is <a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/index.php">just around the corner</a> and if you haven't booked yet, <a href="http://evbk.software-acumen.com/makebooking.php?event=CG2011">you should hurry up</a> - a few places are still available!</p>

<p>Quite a number of my colleagues at itemis have been busy preparing for this conference in the past few weeks. Besides working hard to hit the <a href="http://wiki.eclipse.org/Indigo/Simultaneous_Release_Plan">Eclipse Release Train milestone for Indigo on June 22nd</a>, the Xtext team brushed up their hands-on sessions "<a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=17">Xtext Take I: Creating Code Generators with Xtend2</a>" and "<a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=16">Xtext Take II: Crafting Domain Specific Languages with Xtext and Xbase</a>". If you've been using Xtext, you're well aware of the power you have at your disposal with this tool. Xbase and Xtend2, however, take this experience to a whole new level. So make sure to mark your calendar for these two sessions!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>But not only the Xtext team will share their expertise at CG2011 - Markus and Karsten will be also be in town to give hands-on tutorials and report from their experience:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=22">Type Systems for DSLs (Markus Völter)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=8">Graphiti + Xtext: mixing graphical and textual DSLs for sprayers/designers (Karsten Thoms / Bernhard Merkle)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=5">Introduction to JetBrains Meta Programming System (MPS) (Markus Völter)</a></li>
</ul>


<p>The finale of the conference will be a panel discussion hosted by Markus on the topic of "<a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=20">Models, DSLs, Transformations: The Next 5 years</a>" - this should be a very interesting and lively discussion!</p>

<p><a href="http://lanyrd.com/people/hbehrens/">Heiko</a> <a href="http://lanyrd.com/people/peterfriese/">and I</a> will present "<a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=28">Cross-Platform Mobile Development with DSLs</a>" - a <a href="http://lanyrd.com/2011/cg2011/sdpgm/">fast-paced and fun mixture of slides, live coding (or modeling, if you will), videos and audience interaction</a>. Yes, that's right - the audience will be part of the show. Make sure to bring your web-enabled mobile phone and get the chance to win a price!</p>

<p>To keep track of the conference program(me), we at <a href="http://mobile.itemis.com">itemis mobile</a> have been busy to create a conference planner for your iOS and Android powered mobile phones. Here are the download links:</p>

<ul>
<li>Apple App Store: <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/code-generation-2011/id436689925?mt=8">Code Generation 2011</a></li>
<li>Android Market Place: <a href="https://market.android.com/details?id=de.itemis.mobile.android.cg2011&amp;feature=search_result">Code Generation 2011</a></li>
</ul>


<p><ul class="gallery">
<li><a href="/images/2011-05-21-code-generation-2011-dont-miss-out/cg2011.png" class="fancybox" rel="gallery-f9049cdceaffaf2ba66743d40d991d29" title="Code Generation 2011 Apps for iPhone and Android"><img src="/thumbs/cg2011_300x300.png" alt="Code Generation 2011 Apps for iPhone and Android" /></a></li>
</ul></p>

<p>If you like the apps, please use the feedback feature of the respective store. Got comments or suggestions for improvement? <a href="mailto:mobile@itemis.de">Drop us a note</a> or track us down at the conference (best chance to see us: <a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2011/sessioninfo.php?session=28">come to our talk</a> ;-) ).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Save a Tree, Put EclipseCon 2011 in Your Pocket]]></title>
    <link href="http://peterfriese.github.io/save-a-tree-put-eclipsecon-2011-in-your-pocket/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-25T22:15:57+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://peterfriese.github.io/save-a-tree-put-eclipsecon-2011-in-your-pocket</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After the huge success of the mobile apps for Eclipse Summit Europe, we decided to provide mobile apps for EclipseCon 2011, too. So instead of using a printed copy of the conference program, you can browse the schedule on your smart phone - wherever you are!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This year, we're providing a rather impressive lineup of mobile apps for iPhone, iPod Touch, iPad (thanks to <a href="http://www.compeople.eu/blog/?p=786">Christian Campo who created a stand-alone iPad app</a>), BlackBerry (<a href="http://ekkes-apps.org/">Ekke is working on a updated version, AFAIK</a>), and all other smart phones that feature a browser.</p>

<p>All apps allow you to browse the program, select your favorite talks and get to know the speakers (with headshots so you recognise them in the hallways). We also have included maps of the convention center as well as Santa Clara.</p>

<p>For a first glimpse, watch our video:</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/20377509 "></iframe></div></p>

<p>As of today, both iPhone and Android users can download the apps from the Apple App Store respectively the Android Marketplace. Here are the links:</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://bit.ly/econ2011iphone">EclipseCon 2011 iPhone App</a></li>
<li><a href="http://bit.ly/econ2011android">EclipseCon 2011 Android App</a></li>
</ol>


<p>If you don't own an iPhone or Android, you can always use the HTML-only version of the conference program available at <a href="http://bit.ly/econ2011html">http://bit.ly/econ2011html</a>.</p>

<p>The iPad and BlackBerry apps will be available soon, so stay tuned!</p>

<p>By the way, if <strong>you</strong> run a conference and are interested in having an app like this, <a href="http://mobile.itemis.com">get in touch with us</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
