<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Life | Peter Friese]]></title>
  <link href="http://peterfriese.github.io/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://peterfriese.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-10T03:34:49+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://peterfriese.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Peter Friese]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Joining itemis]]></title>
    <link href="http://peterfriese.github.io/joining-itemis/"/>
    <updated>2008-02-19T11:33:20+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://peterfriese.github.io/joining-itemis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Effective February 1st, 2008, I left my <a href="http://www.gentleware.com/">former employer</a> and <a href="https://www.xing.com/profile/Peter_Friese">joined</a> <a href="http://www.itemis.de/">itemis</a>.</p>

<p>There are many reasons for this step, and I don't want to go into too much detail, so here are the two most important ones:</p>

<p>First of all, I had to do a lot of travel in my recent position at Gentleware. Actually, I like traveling quite much - as you get around interesting places and meet  a lot of interesting people - especially if you are a software architect (which is a synonym for "information hub" :-) ). However, with three small children, this meant a lot of hassle and tears. Wrong timing, one might argue. Maybe I'll hit the road again when the kids are older. The new position does not require that much traveling, so I'll be at home most evenings which is great for my family (and also for me).</p>

<p>As you may know, <a href="http://www.itemis.de">itemis</a> is quite committed to Model Driven Software Development (MDSD). The majority of projects they work on rely on MDA/MDSD technology. Not only is itemis a user of model driven technology, but also do they heavily contribute to open source projects in this area. Itemis employees are committers on projects like <a href="http://ww.openarchitectureware.org">openArchitectureWare</a>, <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/modeling/">Eclipse Modeling Project</a> and Fornax. Since the company management has identified "innovation management" as one of their top duties, they consequently launched a <a href="http://www.itemis.de/presse/5287/neue-niederlassung-in-kiel.html">new branch office in Kiel</a> with a group of employees who are dedicated to working on open source modeling tools.  As working on open source projects is something I really enjoy and since I believe model driven development is a very hot topic, I decided to switch companies and join this team.</p>

<p>I learned a lot at Gentleware and am very grateful for the experiences I was able to make there.</p>

<p>Now, I am looking forward to creating the upcoming version 5.0 of <a href="http://ww.openarchitectureware.org">openArchitectureWare</a> together with my colleagues (<a href="https://www.xing.com/profile/Sven_Efftinge">Sven Efftinge</a>, <a href="https://www.xing.com/profile/Jan_Koehnlein">Jan Köhnlein</a>, <a href="https://www.xing.com/profile/Dennis_Huebner2">Dennis Hübner</a>, <a href="https://www.xing.com/profile/Torsten_Krohn">Torsten Krohn</a>) here in <a href="http://www.kitz-kiel.de/">Kiel</a>. Expect to hear exciting things in the following weeks and months. We started a team blog you might want to subscribe to: <a href="http://apps.itemis.de/roller/itemislabkiel">http://apps.itemis.de/roller/itemislabkiel </a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Three things about me you might be surprised to hear about...]]></title>
    <link href="http://peterfriese.github.io/three-things-about-me-you-might-be-surprised-to-hear-about/"/>
    <updated>2007-01-07T23:13:08+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://peterfriese.github.io/three-things-about-me-you-might-be-surprised-to-hear-about</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to <a href="http://www.mwiesner.com/index.php/2007/01/02/3-dinge-uber-mich/">Michael</a>, it's about time to let you know that...</p>

<ol>
<li><p>I started my programming career at the age of 12, when my father bought a Phillips MSX home computer. It had a very <a href="http://www.msxgamesbox.com/museum/museum/philips/PhilipsVG8000.jpg">slick looking case</a>, and you could write programs in some ancient version of Microsoft Basic.</p></li>
<li><p>When I was 18, I worked in a cinema. Back then, we were using Ernemann film projectors. My duty was to start the film and to crossfade from one projector to the other one as soon as you could see a white spot in the upper right area of the screen. Here is a <a href="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Filmprojektor#.C3.9Cberblendbetrieb">detailled description</a> of how it works exactly.</p></li>
<li><p>A red umbrella (of the <a href="http://www.knirps.de/">Knirps </a>brand) played a major role in getting to know the girl who is now my wife. I lost that umbrella at a friend's birthday party. When I wanted to fetch the umbrella some days later, that friend was on holiday, but Anne was there to hand out the umbrella. I guess we both would never have thought fetching that umbrella would take so long - we spent the whole day together.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Well, who's next in line? <a href="http://voelterblog.blogspot.com/index.html">Markus</a>, <a href="http://www.mbohlen.de/blog/">Matthias</a> and <a href="http://slontech.blogspot.com/">Boris</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leaving Lufthansa Systems]]></title>
    <link href="http://peterfriese.github.io/leaving-lufthansa-systems/"/>
    <updated>2007-01-04T01:19:02+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://peterfriese.github.io/leaving-lufthansa-systems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am leaving <a href="http://www.lhsystems.com">Lufthansa Systems</a> to join <a href="http://www.gentleware.com">Gentleware</a>.</p>

<p>I joined <a href="http://www.lufthansa.com">Lufthansa</a> in August 1996, when I started my studies in computer sciences at <a href="http://www.nordakademie.de">Nordakademie,</a> Elmshorn. After finishing my studies in early 2000, I started my career as a software engineer with <a href="http://www.lhsystems.com">Lufthansa Systems</a>. My first team developed a tool that helped administrators to install Windows PCs unattended. Most of the code was written in Delphi and DOS Batch. After 1 year, I had the opportunity to join another team who were writing enterprise applications in Java. Although I had never written a single line of Java code before, I was given the chance to join the team (mostly because I had some experience with distributed systems and CORBA). The team was rather small when I joined (only three developers, including me, and one boss), but grew up to 15 developers in about 2 years. We had some good fun writing J2EE applications (and frameworks).</p>

<p>In 2004, I was looking for a tool thet helped me to quickly create a Struts-based application and came across <a href="http://www.andromda.org">AndroMDA</a>. This was an important step on my way into the world of model driven software development. I started using AndroMDA in my J2EE projects, and soon started contributing patches to AndroMDA. Sortly after, I was invited to join AndroMDA as a committer.</p>

<p>Gentleware is a well-known company in the realm of modeling tools and I first met Gentleware's CEO Marco Boger at JAX 2004 when Matthias Bohlen and I gave a talk on AndroMDA. In 2006, Gentleware were looking for a Software Architect to join their team and help them to further develop their new Eclipse based roundtrip engineering tool <a href="http://www.gentleware.com/apollo.html">Apollo</a>.</p>

<p>My main areas of work in my new job will be to help make Apollo a great UML tool that integrates with model driven approaches like MDA and MDSD. Also, I will serve as a Software Architect on J2EE projects.</p>

<p>If you happen to be at OOP 2007 in Munich, just drop by the Gentleware booth and say hi. I will be there not only to present <a href="http://www.gentleware.com/apollo.html">Apollo</a> and <a href="http://www.gentleware.com/products.html">Poseidon</a> (our modelling tools), but also to give a talk on <a href="http://www.sigs-datacom.de/sd/kongresse/oop_2007/program.php?cat=session&amp;ID=13">Open Source MDA</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jonas Aaron is here!]]></title>
    <link href="http://peterfriese.github.io/jonas-aaron-is-here/"/>
    <updated>2006-07-26T21:58:40+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://peterfriese.github.io/jonas-aaron-is-here</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/wp-content/downloads/family/jonas/jonas.jpg" alt="Jonas" /></p>

<p>Today at 3:26 in the morning, Anne gave birth to Jonas Aaron Friese, our third son. Both are well (and a little bit tired).</p>

<p>You, LORD, brought me safely through birth,  and you protected me when I was a baby at my mother's breast.
From the day I was born, I have been in your care, and from the time of my birth, you have been my God.
(Psalm 22, 9+10)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Earth rocks!]]></title>
    <link href="http://peterfriese.github.io/google-earth-rocks/"/>
    <updated>2005-08-09T00:04:13+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://peterfriese.github.io/google-earth-rocks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the german news magazine "<a href="http://www.spiegel.de/">Der SPIEGEL</a>", I read a quite promising article about <a href="http://earth.google.com/">Google Earth</a>. Today, I gave it a try and was impressed by the smoothness of the tool right away.  <a href="http://f3.tobject.de/wp-content/downloads/googleearth/Homes.kmz">Here is a file</a> that shows you where I have lived so far.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
